Finding Aid of the Robert G. Neumann papers LSC.1344
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robert G. Neumann papers
1920-1990
UCLA Library Special Collections
Neumann family
LSC.1344
116.5 linear feet (225 boxes, 4 cartons, and 33 oversize boxes)
0.5 linear feet (1 unprocessed vinyl record box)
1 audiovisual carriers (1 open reel audiotape)
Robert Gerhard Neumann (b.1916) was a professor (1947- ), director of the Institute of International and Foreign Studies (1959-65), and chairman of the Atlantic and West European Program (1965-66) at UCLA. He was also a member of the central committee of the California Republican Party (1954-60), U.S. Ambassador to Afghanistan (1966-73) and U.S. Ambassador to Morocco (1973-76). In 1976, he served as senior associate at the Center for Strategic and International Studies, Georgetown University. Marlen E. Neumann (1915-1997) served as president of the Los Angeles League of Women Voters (1957-59), was a member of the board of directors of the United Nations Association of Los Angeles (1959- ), and was a member of the McCone Commission that investigated the Watts riots of 1965. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, clippings, books, published material and Ph.D dissertation by Dr. Neumann, photographs and photograph albums, clippings, research materials and notes, notecards, videocassettes, audiocassettes, speeches, college yearbooks, tax files, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and miscellaneous ephemera.
Restrictions on Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Material in the collection is unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (AskLSC@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942334933606533
Biography
Robert Gerhard Neumann was born on January 2, 1916 in Vienna, Austria; diplome superieur, University of Rennes, 1936; diploma, Consular Academy, 1937 and Geneva School of International Studies, 1937; attended University of Vienna, 1938; MA, Amherst College, 1940; Ph.D, University of Minnesota, 1946; married Marlen Eldredge, July 27, 1941; he became an instructor, State Teachers College, Oshkosh, Wisconsin, 1941-42; lecturer, University of Wisconsin, 1946-47; assistant professor (1947-52), associate professor (1952-58), in 1958, professor, director of the Institute of International and Foreign Studies (1959-65), and chairman of the Atlantic and West European Program (1965-66), UCLA; member of the central committee of the California Republican Party, 1954-60; became U.S. Ambassador to Afghanistan (1966-73) and U.S. Ambassador to Morocco (1973-76); served as senior associate at the Center for Strategic and International Studies, Georgetown University, beginning. in 1976; publications include The government of the German Federal Republic (1966) and European and comparative government (4th ed., 1968); Marlen E. Neumann was born on December 20, 1915 in Miraj, India; BA, Rollins College, 1936; MA in international relations, Yale University, 1941; served as president of the Los Angeles League of Women Voters, 1957-59, as a member of the board of directors of the United Nations Association of Los Angeles beginning in 1959, and as a member of the McCone Commission that investigated the Watts riots of 1965; she died in July 1997 in Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, diaries, manuscripts, clippings, books, published material and Ph.D dissertation by Dr. Neumann, photographs and photograph albums, clippings, research materials and notes, notecards, videocassettes, audiocassettes, speeches, college yearbooks, tax files, scrapbooks, memorabilia, and miscellaneous ephemera.
Ambassadors' spouses -- United States -- Archives.; Ambassadors -- United States -- Archives.; Women civic leaders -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Political science teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Neumann, Marlen E. -- Archives; Neumann, Robert G. -- Archives; Neumann family -- Archives; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Political Science--Faculty
- Robert Neumann
  - Afghanistan
    - Personal Files (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)
      - A - C. (Box 1)
      - D - H. (Box 2)
      - I - M (no.1). (Box 3)
      - M (no.2) - S (no.1). (Box 4)
      - S (no.2) - Z. (Box 5)
    - Kabul representation, various reports and booklets. (Box 6)
    - State / USIA recreation association, Miscellaneous correspondence, Christmas card list, books. (Box 7)
    - Speeches. (Box 8)
    - Tapes of music, photographs. (Box 9)
    - Office logs, photographs. (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, including information on Afghanistan. (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous information, appointment diaries (), and files: miscellaneous correspondence, personnel, travel, White House., 1970-1971 (Box 13)
  - Afghanistan / Morocco
    - Correspondence and oddments re Afghanistan and Morocco. (Box 11)
  - Morocco
    - Personal files (2), alphabetical files A - H., 1975-1976 (Box 14)
    - Alphabetical files, I - U. (Box 15)
    - Alphabetical files, V - Z, desk diary (), photographs, and lecture material., 1975 (Box 16)
    - campaign., 1980 (Box 20)
  - Afghanistan / Morocco / Saudi Arabia
    - Tapes of speeches and other events, papers re Saudi Arabia story., 1981; (3 tapes) (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
  - Reagan Campaign
    - 1980. (Box 21, Box 22, Box 23)
  - Personal Career
    - Clippings, correspondence, photographs and memorabilia., 1930s-1950s. (Box 24, Box 25, Box 26)
    - Memorabilia, photographs and correspondence, A - K., 1950s. (Box 27)
    - Clippings, correspondence, photographs and memorabilia., 1930s-1970s. (Box 28)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes Dulles letters, State Department.
  - Personal Files
    - Memorabilia, photographs, correspondence mostly from family (), War diary (), unidentified tape., 1940-1959 1944 (Box 29)
    - Income tax, early career, military and emigration history, etc., 1940s-1950s. (Box 30)
    - From NARS. (Box 40, Box 41)
  - Professional
    - Correspondence., 1957-1966 (Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37)
      - 1957-1966. (Box 31)
      - 1956-1964. (Box 32)
      - 1957-1959. (Box 33)
      - 1959-1964. (Box 34)
      - 1960-1964. (Box 35)
      - 1962-1967. (Box 36)
      - 1964-1965. (Box 37)
    - European government (book)., (Copy) (Box 36)
    - Publications, proceedings of meetings of Committee on international and Comparative Studies., 1971. (Box 38)
    - UC correspondence, A - Z. "Think File," bio bib, etc., 1960s-1970s. (Box 39)
    - Speeches, conference and seminar material., 1978-1985. (Box 132)
    - Speeches, newspaper and magazine articles., 1981-1984. (Box 134)
    - Ambassadorial correspondence and autobiography (typed draft), 1978-1986. (Box 130)
    - Correspondence. (Box 48)
      Including with Nixon and Eisenhower (1950).
  - Personal, Professional
    - Research material, correspondence, memorabilia. (Box 42)
  - Personal, Professional[?]
    - Correspondence., 1938-1946 (Box 43, Box 44, Box 45)
      - 1938-1942. (Box 43)
      - 1946. (Box 44, Box 45)
    - Political contributions, Bologna center. (Box 46)
  - Professional[?]
    - Correspondence., 1950s. (Box 47)
      Including Nixon letters ("N").
    - Printed research material. (Box 53, Box 54)
    - Research material, Nuremburg trial transcripts. (Box 55, Box 56)
    - Books. (Box 57, Box 58)
    - Research notes and papers and news clippings., 1950s. (Box 59)
    - Notes on cards. (Box 60, Box 61)
    - Research material. Dissertation. (Box 119)
      General note
      Donated 1984 May.
    - Research material. (Box 120, Box 121)
  - Algeria
    - Research material., 1950s. (Box 49, Box 50)
  - Germany
    - Research material and notes., ca. 1945-1958. (Box 51, Box 52)
  - Middle East
    - Manuscripts and printed research material., 1980s. (Box 131)
  - Letters, memos, etc., early 1990s. (Box 154)
  - Notes, clippings, etc. (Box 155)
    Some on L.A. riots. 1992.
  - Notes, primarily on Germany., 1980s-1990s. (Box 156)
  - Note cards on various topics., v.d. (Box 166)
  - Alphabetical files, A - L., 1996-1997. (Box 183)
  - Pocket diaries., 1950s-1970s[?] (Box 189, Box 190)
    - 1950s-1960s[?]. (Box 189)
    - 1960s-1970s[?]. (Box 190)
  - Speeches and recordings., v.d. (Box 191, Box 192)
  - Council of American Ambassadors., primarily 1990s[?]. (Box 193)
  - Ambassadorial items., primarily 1990s. (Box 194)
    Including Morocco.
  - Position papers from others, etc., primarily 1990s. (Box 195)
  - Miscellaneous publications., v.d. (Box 197)
    [Also], manuscript of Recollections Out of My Life (typescript, 59 leaves), n.d.
  - Day books, letters, etc., v.d. (Box 201)
    [Also], Family album. 1950s.
  - Research publications, German and Arab (), Marlen in Rabat, UNE., ca. 1990s v.d. (Box 202)
  - Who's who, household shipments. Kabul., 1970s. (Box 205, Box 206)
  - SVCA Board, CSIS expenses, writings and clippings., v.d. (Box 224)
  - Afghanistan materials, photographs, etc., v.d. (Box 230)
  - Afghanistan, Morocco materials., v.d. (Box 231)
  - Research notes, Germany, Arabia, D.I.S. consultant,, etc., 1980 (Box 250)
  - Publications and clippings, diplomatic corps., v.d. (Box 251)
  - Video tapes and audio tape., v.d. (Box 252)
    Not all videos are of RN.
  - Alphabetical files, M - Z., 1990s. (Box 258)
- Robert Neumann[?]
  - Afghanistan
    - Photograph albums, guest book. (Box 142)
  - Professional[?]
    - Newspaper and magazine articles, 1974-1986. (Box 133)
    - Tape recording (unidentified). (Box 143)
  - Morocco
    - Photograph album. (Box 144)
    - Publications AND journals., 1980s[?]. (Box 145)
    - Photo album. Morocco., 1975. (Box 146)
      [Also], 10.5" audio tape.
    - Video and audio recordings of in those in which RN major participant. (Box 147, Box 148, Box 149)
  - Alphabetical files., 1977. (Box 225, Box 226)
    - A - F., 1977. (Box 225)
    - G - R., 1977. (Box 226)
  - Notecards., v.d. (Box 244)
- Marlen Neumann
  - Conference notebooks., v.d. (Box 153)
  - Daily appointment books., 1950s-. (Box 165)
  - Cards, letters from RN, etc., v.d. (Box 180)
  - Genealogy notes., v.d. (Box 181)
  - Geneaology and Afghanistan materials., v.d. (Box 182)
  - Plays directed., 1946, 1968. (Box 184)
    Angel Street, The Barrets of Wimpole Street.
  - Weekly pocket diaries., 1980s-1990s. (Box 185)
  - Notes on letters received (Box 186, Box 187, Box 188)
    - 1980s[?]. (Box 186, Box 187)
    - A - D., 1980s[?]. (Box 188)
  - Genealogy and commonplace notes., v.d. (Box 198)
  - Early writings, ideas, playbooks and address books., v.d. (Box 207, Box 208)
  - Correspondence., v.d. (Box 218, Box 219)
    - A - B and out of order., v.d. (Box 218)
    - C - H and unfoldered., v.d. (Box 219)
  - Conference notebooks, writing group and statements on Morocco., v.d. (Box 220)
  - Early school, Christmas, commonplace notes, Jidda and PARSA., v.d. (Box 227)
  - Notebooks, Institute of Children's Literature, Welcome to Afghanistan[?]., v.d. (Box 228)
  - Kabul info for service wives, Moroccan ephemera, Foreign Service., v.d. (Box 229)
  - Anne Smith materials and photos., v.d. (Box 238)
  - Anne Smith and Smith family., v.d. (Box 239)
  - Anne Smith and Pauline Smith., v.d. (Box 240)
  - Anne Smith materials., v.d. (Box 243)
  - Women in the Middle East, Foreign Service, etc., v.d. (Box 245)
  - Household effects, guest lists, etc., 1980s. (Box 249)
  - Personal and family items., v.d. (Box 253)
  - Appointments, photos, etc., v.d., 1950s-1960s. (Box 254)
  - Eldrege daybooks () and McCone report items., 1920s v.d. (Box 255)
  - Alphabetical files. (Box 256, Box 257)
    (Received in disorder)
  - Family pictures, notes and cards, early notes and lectures., v.d. (Box 259)
  - Condo lawsuit and personal., v.d. (Box 260)
  - Publications and texts., v.d. (Box 261)
- Marlen Neumann[?]
  - India
    - Clippings and ephemera. (Box 135-138, 140)
- Marlen and Robert Neumann
  - Personal
    - Family letters., 1939-1941. (Box 112)
      Also correspondence from Eisenhower, Nixon, Nasser to Mr. Neumann. 1960s.
    - Tax files. (Box 113)
    - Family correspondence., 1977-1980. (Box 114)
    - Scrapbooks, photographs, correspondence. (Box 115)
    - Family correspondence, etc. (Box 116)
    - Correspondence with each other. (Box 124)
    - Letters., 1942-1945. (Box 125)
    - Letters., 1947-1963. (Box 127)
  - Personal[?]
    - Memorabilia, miscellaneous ephemera, clippings, photographs, etc. (Box 117)
  - Certificates and signed photographs., v.d. (Box 199)
  - Portrait of Marlen, college pennants, maps, etc., v.d. (Box 200)
  - General Electric (Tempo), Faxes, Photos, Marlen correspondence ()., 1972- 1970s-1990s. (Box 203)
  - Bicenntenial inaugural, cards, photos, certificates., v.d. (Box 209)
  - Hostess books with menus, RN Dartmouth conference notes., v.d., 1997. (Box 210)
  - Memorabilia, including menus., 1930s-. (Box 211)
  - Sketch books, photo albums, etc., v.d. (Box 212)
  - Anne Smith items and photos (), Marlen early scrapbooks., 1920s v.d. (Box 213)
  - Marlen business correspondence, dolls, resumes, Robert resumes., v.d. (Box 214)
  - Letters R to M to / from Rabat, tape letters., primarily 1971. (Box 221)
  - Letters to / from, to / from Rabat, Jidda, Cairo, etc., 1970s. (Box 222)
  - Saud Arabia materials., 1977-. (Box 223)
    Includes Women in foreign service, etc.
  - Morocco scrapbook., v.d. (Box 232)
  - Afghanistan scrapbook., v.d. (Box 233, Box 234)
  - Kabul scrapbook., v.d. (Box 235)
  - Afghanistan., v.d. (Box 236)
  - Alphabetical files, S - Z., 1990s. (Box 237)
  - Marlen to Robert, Kabul., v.d. (Box 246, Box 247)
  - Household effects, travel clips, notes in Arabic (), etc., 1981 (Box 248)
  - Travel ephemera, theatre programs., v.d. (Box 262)
- Marlen and Robert Neumann[?]
  - Personal
    - Correspondence. (Box 122)
  - Personal, Professional[?]
    - Correspondence and photographs, invitations to ceremonies., 1965-1981. (Box 129)
  - Library catalog cards., 1940s[?].; (Box not full) (Box 215)
- Neumann Family
  - General
    - 1987-1991. (Box 151, Box 152)
      Mid East Travel in Box 152.
  - Books., v.d. (Box 157, Box 158)
  - Letters and cards., 1980s. (Box 167, Box 168)
  - Photographs., v.d. (Box 169, Box 170)
    - v.d. (Box 169)
    - Primarily official., v.d. (Box 170)
  - Negatives, primarily, v.d., 1920s-1930s[?]. (Box 171)
  - Photographs, primarily official, datebook, etc., v.d., 1986. (Box 172)
  - Primarily negatives. [?]., v.d., 1920s-1930s (Box 173)
  - Christmas cards., 1980s. (Box 174)
    Includes cards from the Bush family, King of Jordan, etc.
  - Clippings., v.d. (Box 175)
  - Army cap, academic robes, etc. (Both Newmans?). (Box 176)
  - Plaques., v.d. (Box 177)
  - Marlen letters to parents (), Robert National Politics[?]., 1966-1969 v.d. (Box 178)
    Includes letter from Brent Scowcroft, The White House, etc.
  - Appointment books, etc., 1960[?]. (Box 179)
  - Passports and Moroccan albums., 1950s-1970s. (Box 196)
  - Eldredge family sketches. Neumann parents anniversary., 1930s, 1960s. (Box 216)
  - Scrapbooks. (Marlen in hospital), event scrapbook., 1982 1980s. (Box 217)
  - Faxes and cards. AAFSW (), etc., 1990s. 1987 (Box 241)
  - Faxes and cards., 1990s. (Box 242)
- Neumann Family[?]
  - Note cards on various topics., v.d. (Box 159, Box 160, Box 161)
  - Note cards on correspondents., v.d. (Box 162, Box 163, Box 164)
- Marlen / Anne Smith[?]
  - Correspondence and notes., 1930s. (Box 150)
- Marlen Neumann / Anne Smith / Robert Neumann
  - Snapshots, Address Books
    - RN Dartmouth notes, photo Grandmother Smith, etc., 1986 and n.d. (Box 204)